A Finding Aid to the Rudolph Schaeffer Papers, 1880s-1997, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Printed Material, 1906-1994; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 19, 22
  - Produced by Rudolph Schaeffer, 1935-1942; 9.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Books, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Sunset's Flower Arrangement Book by Nell True Welch, Edited and Foreword by Rudolph Schaeffer, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Produced by Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, 1920s-1986; 9.2; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries includes items such as school catalogs, announcements and invitations.
    - Calendars of Events, 1955-1957, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Catalogs and Course Announcements, 1920s-1984, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17-23)
    - Course Announcements, circa 1920s-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 24-25)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 1920s-circa 1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Form Letters, 1933-1955, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Lecture Announcements, 1920s-1973, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Newsletter, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Press Release, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Press Releases, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Sample Certificates, Stationery, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Special Event Announcements and Invitations, 1948-1986, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Produced by Others, 1906-1994; 9.3; Archival Resource Key
    Printed material found here is about or mentions Rudolph Schaeffer and his school. Items of note are announcements of courses taught by Schaeffer in Piedmont and San Francisco prior to the opening of his school, theatre programs from productions with sets and some costumes designed by Schaeffer in the early 1920s.
    - About or Mentioning Rudolph Schaeffer, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
      - Announcements of Rudolph Schaeffer Summer School of Design and Handicraft/Rudolph Schaeffer Crafts and Art Studio (Piedmont, Calif.), California School of Fine Arts, 1916-1919, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Book, Miss Aunt Nellie: The Autobiography of Nellie C. Cornish, University of Washington Press, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Clippings, 1910s-1980s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
      - Oversize Clippings About/Mentioning Rudolph Schaeffer, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 15)
      - Oversize Clippings About/Mentioning Rudolph Schaeffer, circa 1940-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Exhibition Announcements, 1922-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Lecture and Workshop Notices, 1916-1959, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous Items, 1906-1986, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection (exhibition catalogs, etc.), 1976-1994, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection, 1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 27)
      - Theater Programs (sets designed by Rudolph Schaeffer), 1920-1925, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Course Curriculum Pamphlets, circa 1914-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 28)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Birthday Invitations, circa 1976-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1921-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - About/Mentioning Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - Advertising, 1920s-1983, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
      - Clippings, 1927-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13-15)
      - Miscellaneous Items, 1928-1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Clippings, Miscellaneous Subjects (art-related), 1932-1987, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Photographs, 1880s-circa 1988; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 8-10, 15, 20, 22, OV 18
  Additional photographs may be found in Series 3: Subject Files and Series 7: Scrapbooks.
  The series is arranged into 8 subseries:
  10.1: Artwork, circa 1907-1980
  10.2: People, 1880s-1980s
  10.3: Places, circa 1907-1983
  10.4: Events, 1937-1976
  10.5: Stage Designs, circa 1920s
  10.6: Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1910-circa 1988
  10.7: Photograph Album, undated
  10.8: Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, circa 1958-circa 1969
  - Artwork, circa 1907-1980; 10.1; Archival Resource Key
    Photographs are of artwork, people, places, events, stage designs, and miscellaneous subjects. Artwork includes some designs by Rudolph Schaeffer, many samples of student work in various media, and views of exhibition installations.
    - Designs, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - Furniture, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - Furniture (Columbus Manual Training School), circa 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Metal Work (including jewelry), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Interior Designs and Arrangements, circa 1930s-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Oversize Interior Designs and Arrangements, circa 1930s-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition Installations, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - "Modern Art Pots for Flowers, Rudolph F. Schaeffer Crafts and Art Studio, Piedmont"), 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art, Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, 1980, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Rocks, Kansas City, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - Student Exhibitions, Rudolph Schaeffer instructor, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
        - California College of Arts and Crafts; Schaeffer's Crafts and Art Studio, Piedmont, circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24)
        - Cornish School?, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
        - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, 1931-1932, 1978, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 26-31)
      - Oriental Art Exhibition (at Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design), 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 32)
      - Women's City Club, San Francisco, Exhibition of Decorative Arts (designed by Rudolph Schaeffer), 1929 or 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33)
      - Unidentified Exhibition(s) (featuring flower arrangements), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Flower Arrangements, 1931-1977, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Models for Student Interior Design Projects, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Paintings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Schaeffer, Rudolph, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
      - Interiors, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 38)
      - Wall Decorations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Screens, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Sculpture, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - People, 1880s-1980s; 10.2; Archival Resource Key
    People portrayed here are mainly Rudolph Schaeffer, the Schaeffer family, friends and students. Of particular note are a photograph of Frank Lloyd Wright's visit to the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and a photograph of Rudolph Schaeffer with Imogen Cunningham.
    - Rudolph Schaeffer, 1880s-1980s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 42-45)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Chang-Dai-Chien, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Classmates, 1899-1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Family (?), circa 1900-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Frank Lloyd Wright and Students, 1958 or 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Imogen Cunningham, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Others, 1913-1914, 1960s-1980s, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 51-53)
    - Family, Parents (Julius and Mary Hirzel Schaeffer), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Others, Individuals and Groups, 1932-1984, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer and Others, circa 1880s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
    - Oversize Photo of Actress Peggy Cuddy, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Places, circa 1907-1983; 10.3; Archival Resource Key
    Places include interior and exterior views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design at its St. Anne Street and Mariposa Street locations, travel pictures of Laguna Beach and Mt. Wilson, and unidentified buildings and landscapes.
    - Buildings, Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Columbus, Ohio, Manual, Training School, circa 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Home of Cousin Karl (?) Schaeffer (interior view), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Laguna Beach, circa 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Landscapes, Unidentified, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Mt. Wilson, 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Mariposa Street, 1970-1981, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - St. Anne Street, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Summer Cabin, Dos Rios, Calif., 1983, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, St. Anne Street, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 18)
    - Home of Fred and Caroline Frey, by Ansel Adams, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Various Locations, circa 1907-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Events, 1937-1976; 10.4; Archival Resource Key
    Among the events depicted are an arts festival, an exhibition opening, a graduation and parties held at the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. Stage sets photographed were designed by Rudolph Schaeffer for productions in San Francisco and Detroit. Among the miscellaneous subjects are horses, Rudolph Schaeffer's collection of Asian art and his headstone in Clare, Michigan.
    - Arts Festival, Aquatic Park, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition Opening, "Selections from the Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Oriental Art," Asian Art Museum of San Francisco, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Graduation, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Parties, 1937-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Stage Designs, circa 1920s; 10.5; Archival Resource Key
    - Detroit ("Pelleas and Melisande," "A Midsummer Night's Dream"), 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - San Francisco, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Children's Theatre of San Francisco (unidentified), 1922 or 1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Civic Auditorium ("Fantasy in Snowland"), 1922 or 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Seattle (The Cornish School?, unidentified), 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Unknown Location(s), Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - A-Z by Title, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
      - Unidentified, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1910-circa 1988; 10.6; Archival Resource Key
    - Automobile, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Christmas Ornaments, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Horses, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection (Asian art), 1986, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Schaeffer Headstone (Clare, Mich.), circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Photograph Albums, circa 1973-1986, undated; 10.7; Archival Resource Key
    One photograph album contains views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design on St. Anne Street, exhibition installations, selections from Rudolph Schaeffer's collection of Asian art, and student work. Another contains views of Schaeffer's garden at the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. The third album is a memorial album of images of Schaeffer.
    - Photograph Album, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Photos of RSSD Garden Summer 1973 by William Woodworth, Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer Remembered, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, circa 1958-circa 1969; 10.8; Archival Resource Key
    - Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Exhibition Installations (Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Rocks, Kansas City), circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Flower Arrangements, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - "Modern Art Pots for Flowers, Rudolph F. Schaeffer Crafts and Art Studio, Piedmont,", 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - People, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer (painting; planting a tree), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer with Others (Frank Lloyd Wright and Students; unidentified), 1958 or 1959, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Places, Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design (Mariposa Street), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)